Finding Aid for Chihiro Kikuchi Papers 1942-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Chihiro Kikuchi papers 1942-1988
Kikuchi, Chihiro, 1914-
7 linear feet
Professor of nuclear engineering at the University of Michigan; specialist in the field of solid-state physics, notably the ruby maser and electron spin resonance; and advocate of nuclear power. Papers include biographical materials; correspondence; electron spin resonance and ruby maser research project files; physics and mathematics notebooks; course files; scientific papers, speeches, and testimonies; and visual materials, mainly intended to accompany lectures.
89171 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Records were first donated by Chihiro Kikuchi (Donor # 7285 ) in January 1986 and the majority of the collection was deposited in 1988.
The collection is open for research.
Chihiro Kikuchi, professor of nuclear engineering at the University of Michigan, was born on September 26, 1914, in Seattle, Washington. He studied at the University of Washington, and received his B.S. in physics in 1939. Continuing in graduate studies at the University of Cincinnati, Kikuchi obtained his M.A. in mathematics in 1943. The following year he completed his Ph.D. in physics at the University of Washington.
Kikuchi began his professional career as a teaching fellow at the University of Washington, 1939-1942. In 1943 he left to teach physics as an instructor at Haverford College. In 1944 he was hired as a laboratory instructor at Michigan State College (now Michigan State University), where he lectured on physics for two years. Appointed an assistant professor in the department of physics in 1946, Kikuchi remained on the faculty at Michigan State College until 1953. For a short period, 1951-1952, he was a visiting professor at Brookhaven National Laboratory.
Through the 1950s, Kikuchi was actively involved in many research projects. In 1953 he accepted an offer to conduct research in the field of solid-state physics as a research physicist at the Naval Research Laboratory, in Washington, D.C. From the Naval Research Laboratory, Kikuchi soon returned to Michigan, in 1955, where he continued experiments in solid-state physics at Willow Run Laboratory (W.R.L.), a facility of the University of Michigan. At W.R.L. he started as a research physicist, but soon became head of the solid-state physics research group which he directed from 1958 to 1959. The most notable projects Kikuchi was involved in at W.R.L. were his research on the ruby maser, research on electron spin resonance, research in quantum electronics, and research on radiation effects in solids.
The research on the ruby maser in particular became a high point of Kikuchi's life. The project involved an original technical solution for the action in a ruby maser which Kikuchi had solved at W.R.L., in December 1957.
In 1959, Kikuchi accepted a position as a full professor in the Nuclear Engineering Department at the University of Michigan, devoting his time mostly to teaching. However, he remained a technical consultant and specialist in research for many institutions, notably, the Naval Research Laboratory, Brookhaven National Laboratory, the Defense Atomic Support Agency (DASA), the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA), and others.
In the position of a technical specialist, Kikuchi was assigned by the IAEA to give lectures at the Tsing Hua University in Taiwan in 1964. As a visiting professor he lectured at the Kyoto University in Japan, 1969-1970. For the Institute of Atomic Energy at Sao Paulo, Brazil, he lectured repeatedly in 1974, and 1976 through 1979.
Since the early seventies Professor Kikuchi concentrated on public issues of nuclear power and, as he put it, on the "strange American public reaction to nuclear power." His interests in pro-nuclear power issues dominated his activities through the eighties and lasted until his death in 1988.
During his academic career Professor Kikuchi published numerous articles on various topics in the field of solid-state physics, among which the research papers on ruby maser and electron spin resonance experiments are noteworthy.
Kikuchi's Papers consist of 7 linear feet of material documenting Professor Kikuchi's research and academic career over a time span of forty years. The bulk of the collection consists of the lectures Kikuchi gave in the Department of Nuclear Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1959-1986. The material from 1956 to 1959 consists of research papers on the ruby maser developed at the Willow Run Laboratory, a facility of the University of Michigan. The papers generated in the 1970s and 1980s reflect mostly Kikuchi's academic and public involvement in pro-nuclear power advocacy.
The papers have been rearranged and organized in eight major series: Biographical (0.1 linear ft); Correspondence, consisting of personal letters from 1942, professional letters from 1949-1950, 1958-1964, and 1972-1988, (0.3 linear ft); Research Projects, arranged chronologically, (0.5 linear ft); Printed Technical Reports by the Department of Engineering, (0.5 linear ft); Notebooks (0.5 linear ft); Lectures for nuclear engineering courses and other topics (3.5 linear ft); Papers 1969-1988 (1 linear ft); and Visual Material (0.6 linear ft), consisting of 99 glass plates, 205 slides, 8 photoprints, and 2 cartoons, all of which relate to Kikuchi's academic activities.
Subjects:
Electron paramagnetic resonance.; Kikuchi, Chihiro, 1914-; Masers.; Nuclear energy.; Nuclear engineering.; Physics.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Nuclear Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Willow Run Laboratories.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Kikuchi, Chihiro, 1914-; Masers.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Nuclear Engineering.; University of Michigan. Willow Run Laboratories.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  - Resumes, personal data, lists of publications (Box 1)
  - "Retreat from Moscow" (autobiography) (Box 1)
  - "My Life" (autobiography by Kikuchi's father) (Box 1)
  - Distinguished Alumnus Award from the Broadway Alumni Association, Seattle, Washington August 1966 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Personal 1942 (Box 1)
  - Professional
    - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1988, 16 folders (Box 1)
- Research Projects
  - Electron Spin Resonance (E.S.R.) Research
    - Spin Resonance Amplifiers, February1957 (Box 1)
    - Sum Rules and Relative Intensities for Paramagnetic Ions of Spin 3/2 June 1959 (Box 1)
    - Resonance Absorption of Paramagnetic Ions with Spin 5/2:CaCO3:Mn August 1959 (Box 1)
    - Spin Resonance of V2+,V3+,V4+,in Al2O3 November 1959 (Box 1)
    - Crystal Structure of Al2O3 1962 (Box 1)
  - Ruby Maser Research
    - Maser Action in Ruby (letters) 1958-1964 (Box 1)
    - Ruby Maser (clippings) 1958-1970 (Box 1)
    - MASAR and MASER April 1957 (Box 1)
    - Proposals for the Investigations of Solid-state MASER System July 1957 (Box 1)
    - Induced Microwave Emission in Ruby 1957 (Box 1)
    - Development of Ruby MASER at the W.R.L. and Future Program June 1958 (Box 1)
    - MASER Action in Ruby June 1958 (Box 1)
    - Studies of Paramagnetic MASER Systems August 1958 (Box 1)
    - Basic Research, MASER, and National Defense 1958 (Box 1)
    - Ruby as a MASER Material May 1959 (Box 1)
    - A Low-noise X-Band Radiometer Using MASER 1959 (Box 1)
    - History of the Three Level Solid-state MASER (in tabular form) 1960 (Box 1)
    - Papers on History and Development of Ruby MASER at the Willow Run Laboratory 1960 (Box 1)
    - Proposal to the Air Force Office of Scientific Research December 1961 (Box 1)
    - Papers on Ruby MASER and LASER, September1962 (Box 1)
    - Ruby MASER and LASER. Visit to Bell Telephone Laboratories October 1962 (Box 1)
    - Ruby MASER and LASER 1964 (Box 1)
      (speech)
    - Ruby MASER and LASER 1964 (Box 1)
      (personal account of its history)
    - The Story of the Ruby MASER August 1964 (Box 1)
    - Story of Ruby MASER 1979 (Box 1)
      (reprint of a personal account)
    - The LASER History Project 1985-1986 (Box 1)
      (letters with attachments)
    - Ruby MASER and Deep-Space Exploration October 1987 (Box 1)
    - Ruby MASER and Deep-Space Exploration, 1987 (Box 1)
      (transparencies, charts, graphs)
  - Willow Run Laboratories (W.R.L.)
    - Memos on Research Program 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Program History March 1970 (Box 1)
    - Articles on Glass Research 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Articles on Electron Spin Resonance and Environmental Issues 1956-1982 (Box 1)
- Printed Technical Reports (Department of Engineering)
  - 1963-1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Notebooks
  - 1950-1970, 22 volumes (Box 2)
    (Miscellaneous notes on topics of mathematics and physics)
- Lectures
  - Engineering Summer Conference on Radiation Effects in Semiconductors (Box 3)
    (an intensive short course)
  - Chemistry 207 (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Engineering 100, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Engineering 195 (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Engineering 311 (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Engineering 400, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Engineering 411 (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Engineering 422 (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Engineering 490, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Engineering 490/590, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Engineering 511 (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Engineering 512, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Engineering 570 (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Engineering 611 (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Engineering 612 (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Engineering 622 (Box 5)
  - Nuclear Engineering 421, 470, 512, 570, 622, 670 (Box 5)
    (fragments)
  - Introduction to Laser-Maser Theory (Box 5)
  - Introduction to Reactor Physics (Box 5)
  - Nuclear Power, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Preparing for Peace in the Nuclear Age (Box 5)
  - Quantum Mechanics (Box 5)
  - Radiation and Matter-Part I (Box 5)
  - Radiation Solid-State Physics-Part II (Box 5)
  - Solar/Nuclear Interface (Box 5)
  - Acoustic Radiation (Box 6)
  - Build Up of Reaction Products (Box 6)
  - Chemical vs. Nuclear Reaction Rates (Box 6)
  - Citizenship in Our Technological World (Box 6)
  - CO2 Laser (Box 6)
  - Dielectric Absorption of Biaxial Liquid Crystals (Box 6)
  - Environmental Radioactivity and Genetic Repair (Box 6)
  - Foreign Lectureships
    - Brazil, Sao Paulo Institute of Nuclear Power 1974-1979 (Box 6)
    - Japan, Kyoto University 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - Nuclear Energy and the Green Revolution (Box 6)
  - Nuclear Power Awareness Lecture Series (Box 6)
  - Notes: misc., 11 folders (Box 6)
  - Transparencies, charts, graphs, newspaper clippings, misc., relating to lectures, 12 folders (Box 6)
- Papers, Speeches, and Testimonies
  - Papers
    - Radiation Damage by Thermal Neutrons in Cadmium Compounds 1968 (Box 6)
    - Metastable EPR Centers in Scheelites July 1969 (Box 6)
    - On M. Sinclair's The Social Impact of Nuclear Power 1970 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Bombs; What Should We Do With Them? 1970 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Power; A Model for Developing New Technologies November 1974 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Power; A Model for Developing New Technology for Societal Use 1975 (Box 6)
    - John Fuller's We Almost Lost Detroit 1975 (Box 6)
    - Plutonium 1976 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Nuclear Diplomacy and the Brazilian Technical Community November 1977 (Box 6)
    - The Energy Crisis, The Press, and The Science Teacher December 1977 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Safety vs. Nuclear Security 1978 (Box 6)
    - Solidified High-Level Radioactive Waste Storage in Salt Mines April 1978 (Box 6)
    - The Energy, The Press, and The Science Teacher June 1978 (Box 6)
    - International Issues of Nuclear Power September 1978 (Box 6)
    - Some Common Sense Facts about High-Level Radioactive Wastes November 1978 (Box 6)
    - What Really Happened at Lyons, Kansas? December 1978 (Box 6)
    - Environmental Chemistry and The Management of Radioactive Wastes 1978 (Box 6)
    - Tritium in the Environment 1978 (Box 6)
    - Energy Costs of Pollution Control 1978 (Box 6)
    - The Transition to Solar Energy January 1979 (Box 6)
    - Relative Probabilities as means of Assessing Safety of Nuclear Plants in Developing Nations January 1979 (Box 6)
    - What is High-Level Radioactive Waste January 1979 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Power, A Test of Democracy in Technological Age February 1979 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Power for World April 1979 (Box 6)
    - Energy Costs and Health Risks of Electric Energy Production May 1979 (Box 6)
    - Citizenship in a Democratic Technological Society June 1979 (Box 6)
    - Comments on World Oil Problem, Radioactive Wastes, and Others June 1979 (Box 6)
    - Three Mile Island-2 Transient Feedwater Incident August 1979 (Box 6)
    - Energy Conservation; The Real Los Angeles Experience 1979 (Box 6)
    - Atomic Bombs vs. Nuclear Power Plants 1979 (Box 6)
    - Supplemental Notes on Radioactive Wastes 1979 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear and Solar Energy; Problems and Prospects February 1980 (Box 6)
    - Windmills and Nuclear Power February 1980 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Power; U.S. vs. Foreign May 1980 (Box 6)
    - Reliability Theory of the 3-out-of-4 System... February 1981 (Box 6)
    - Work-Energy; From Human Slaves or Energy Slaves March 1981 (Box 6)
    - Public Perception of Nuclear "Risks" April 1981 (Box 6)
    - Will Energy Conservation Reduce Demand for Electricity? June 1981 (Box 6)
    - The Anglo-saxon 4-letter Words; HEAT vs. WORK October 1981 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Electricity and Your Job Future December 1981 (Box 6)
    - Recent Nuclear Plant Safety Studies 1981 (Box 6)
    - Aren't We Dime Wise Dollar Foolish about Energy? March 1982 (Box 6)
    - Your Job and Nuclear Power March 1982 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Power-Questions and Answers May 1982 (Box 6)
    - Solar/Nuclear Interface Project May 1982 (Box 6)
    - Up Front Natural Resource Commitment Required for the Implementation of Solar Photovoltaic Systems (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Power; Genetic Repair, International Implications, and Other Public Issues November 1982 (Box 6)
    - World Peace in Nuclear Age January 1983 (Box 7)
    - Electricity for Your Job and Your Way of Life October 1983 (Box 7)
    - Teaching Societal Sciences 1983 (Box 7)
    - Consumer vs. Energy Advocacy May 1984 (Box 7)
    - Using Electricity to Save Energy June 1984 (Box 7)
    - Scientist's View of Science Curriculum June 1984 (Box 7)
    - Acid Rain; If you have been John Glenn... June 1984 (Box 7)
    - Chicken is Also a Bird June 1984 (Box 7)
    - Your Lifestyle vs. Thomas and Martha Jefferson June 1984 (Box 7)
    - User vs. Embodied Energy June 1984 (Box 7)
    - Nuclear Free Zone Act; Nuclear Risks in Disguise? October 1984 (Box 7)
    - Nuclear Risks of Nuclear Power and Nuclear Peace November 1984 (Box 7)
    - Nuclear Peace 2010 January 1985 (Box 7)
    - Proposal for Bomb-Grade Plutonium Disposal March 1985 (Box 7)
    - Nuclear Power or Nuclear Bombs;... March 1985 (Box 7)
    - An Ancillary Basis for Nuclear Arms Negotiation... May 1985 (Box 7)
    - Hawks...,Doves,...Owls,... October 1985 (Box 7)
    - Acid Rain October 1985 (Box 7)
    - Preparing for Nuclear Peace November 1985 (Box 7)
    - Binary Logic Decision Tree for the Conflict Resolution... 1985 (Box 7)
    - The Other Side of Nuclear Disarmament February 1986 (Box 7)
    - What to Do to Prepare for Nuclear Peace February 1986 (Box 7)
    - What Can We, Nuclear Engineers Do for Nuclear Peace April 1986 (Box 7)
    - Building Peace in the Nuclear Age July 1986 (Box 7)
    - For Peace in the Nuclear Age September 1986 (Box 7)
    - Preparations for Nuclear Peace; Technical and Public 1986 (Box 7)
    - I'm a Nuke, and Proud of It 1987 (Box 7)
    - Atomic Bomb-A Photographic Record undated (Box 7)
      (photocopies from the book)
  - Speeches
    - Nuclear Power; The Work Horse for the Coming Producer Decade 1980 (Box 7)
    - Nuclear Arms Reduction, Not Just Nuclear Arms Freeze... 1980 (Box 7)
    - Reliability Theory of the 3/4 CLCS 1981 (Box 7)
    - International Nuclear Weapons Proliferation 1981 (Box 7)
  - Testimonies
    - Testimony on H.R. 5318... undated (Box 7)
    - Testimony on H.R .6126, 6289, 6290 1974 (Box 7)
    - Testimony Presented to the Members of the Michigan Democratic Policy Committee 1975 (Box 7)
    - The Pseudo-Conservation Trap... 1980 (Box 7)
    - Statement on Behalf of Scientists and Engineers for Secure Energy 1984 (Box 7)
- Visual Material
  The Visual Materials series consists of photos and slides (most unidentified) relating to the ruby maser and other research and informal portraits of Chichiro Kikuchi.
  - Slides: To accompany lectures on Ruby Maser and Nuclear Power Issues, 205 slides (in 8 boxes) (Box 7)
  - Photographs: Ruby Maser; prof. Kikuchi with Friends, 2 folders; 6 prints (Box 7)
  - Cartoon (Box 7)